Register of the Gennadiĭ Ivanovich Tupit͡syn papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Gennadiĭ Ivanovich Tupit͡syn papers
1900-2004
2005C29
Hoover Institution Archives
7 manuscript boxes (2.9 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, printed matter, postcards, and photographs relating to the promotion of Esperanto, especially in Latvia and the Soviet Union.
Tupit͡syn, Gennadiĭ Ivanovich, 1885-1966.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2005.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Gennadiĭ Ivanovich Tupit͡syn was a Russian Esperantist, linguist, and teacher. He was also an active member of the Latvian Esperanto Society and the Universal Esperanto Association (UEA).
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers consist mostly of correspondence relating to Tupit͡syn's Esperanto teaching activities. Additional materials include writings and printed matter concerning promotion of Esperanto, especially in Latvia and the Soviet Union.
Esperanto--Latvia.; Esperanto--Soviet Union.
- Biographical File, 1914-2004
  - Biographical information, 1959, 2004 (Box-folder 1: 25)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes "Enketo" by G. Tupitsyn and a note by B. Rozenfeld.
  - Esperanto societies membership file, 1914-1958 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Invitations to participate in Esperanto conferences, seminars, and talks, 1926-1959 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    See also: Correspondence.
- Correspondence, 1900-1974
  - Chronological, 1900-1972
    - 1900-1910 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - 1911-1915 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - 1916-1920 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - 1921-1925 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - 1926-1930 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - 1931-1935 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - 1936-1940 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - 1941-1945 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - 1946-1950 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - 1951-1955 (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - 1956-1960 (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - 1961-1965 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - 1966-1972 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Alphabetical, 1907-1974
    - Aizpurits, Aleksandr Eduardovich, 1921-1933 (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - Arbergs, Teodoro, 1934-1961 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - Aref'eva, V., circa 1938 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - Awsrtic, W., 1960 (Box-folder 1: 19)
    - Barash, Liudmila, 1957 (Box-folder 1: 20)
    - Basov, V. N., 1956-1960 (Box-folder 1: 21)
    - Belozerov, Nikolai Mikhailovich, 1957-1967 (Box-folder 1: 22)
    - Berzen, Elfaido, 1939 (Box-folder 1: 23)
    - Blumberg, Nikolai, 1920 (Box-folder 1: 24)
    - Blumberg-Stauer, Ekaterina, 1963-1965 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Bokarev, Evgenii Alekseevich, 1946-1959 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Bormanis, V., 1920-1929 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Bulatov, 1920 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Bulmer, Howard, 1912-1926 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - Cace, Ints, 1957-1961 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - Charrier, Carlos, 1910 (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - Chatelain, Martha, 1933 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    - Cin, Solomon Il'ich, 1956-1974 (Box-folder 2: 9)
    - Cools, A., 1947 (Box-folder 2: 10)
    - Cronkhight, L. W., 1914-1923 (Box-folder 2: 11)
    - Czechowicz, Stanislava, 1960-1965 (Box-folder 2: 12)
    - Daikokuya & Kio Inc., circa 1918 (Box-folder 2: 13)
    - Dalmatov, Petr Ivanovich, 1958-1960 (Box-folder 2: 14)
    - Demchenko, Vasilii Ivanovich, 1956 (Box-folder 2: 15)
    - Demenkov, F. M., 1959-1961 (Box-folder 2: 16)
    - Didkovskii, M., 1931 (Box-folder 2: 17)
    - Dragunovskii, Il'ia Eliseevich, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 2: 18)
    - Drul', I., 1956-1963 (Box-folder 2: 19)
    - Eichenbaum, R., 1919-1921 (Box-folder 2: 20)
    - Erikson, I., 1932 (Box-folder 2: 21)
    - Erkhards (Erhards), 1936 (Box-folder 2: 22)
    - Fedotov, Nikolai Grigor'evich, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 2: 23)
    - Flint, Tekla, 1932 (Box-folder 2: 24)
    - Freidenberg, M., 1920 (Box-folder 2: 25)
    - Gailitis, M., 1959-1960 (Box-folder 2: 26)
    - Gasparian, Alfred Akopovich, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 2: 27)
    - Gaudina, Helma, 1956 (Box-folder 2: 28)
    - Gedrovic, T., 1932 (Box-folder 2: 29)
    - Gold, J., 1956-1960 (Box-folder 2: 30)
    - Goluzin, W., 1956-1959 (Box-folder 2: 31)
    - Gottwald, Elisabeth, 1930 (Box-folder 2: 32)
    - Gramenitskii, Sergei Nikolaevich, 1960-1964 (Box-folder 2: 33)
    - Grebnev, Vadim, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 2: 34)
    - Grigor'ev, G. I., 1956-1961 (Box-folder 2: 35)
    - Grigor'ev, Sergei, 1920-1921 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Grigor'ev, V. L., 1956-1958 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - Grundig, Ferenc, 1930 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - Guarda, Luis E., 1911 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - Guberman, A., 1956 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Gurbanova, A. I., 1957 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Guterman, I. B., 1956-1957 (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - Gutmanis, A., 1957-1959 (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - Hanvai, Endre, 1933 (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - Hazenfuss, Hans, 1947 (Box-folder 3: 10)
    - Helm, Maud, 1914-1946 (Box-folder 3: 11-13)
    - Howe, J. L., 1912 (Box-folder 3: 14)
    - Hudson, Percy G., 1920 (Box-folder 3: 15)
    - Hurd, Luella Josephine, 1910-1934 (Box-folder 3: 16-21)
    - Il'in, Igor' Grigor'evich, 1956 (Box-folder 3: 22)
    - Indra, Talivaldo, 1932-1939 (Box-folder 3: 23)
    - Istomin, 1957 (Box-folder 3: 24)
    - Jevsejeva (Evseeva), Liudmila Ivanovna, 1936-1969 (Box-folder 3: 25-26)
    - Jirgensen, N. J., 1910-1911 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - Johanson, Martin, 1956 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - Johnson, A. H., 1912 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - Jursche, Hilde, 1923-1924 (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - Kapustin, L. G., 1956-1965 (Box-folder 4: 5)
    - Khasheva, Kseniia Aleksandrovna, 1957 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - Kilda, Easl, 1925-1939 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - Kiseleva, E., 1963-1965 (Box-folder 4: 8)
    - Knepper, Helene, 1930 (Box-folder 4: 9)
    - Kolobanov, F., 1958-1959 (Box-folder 4: 10)
    - Kranke, Marianne, 1930-1931 (Box-folder 4: 11)
    - Kulichenko, Afanasii Filippovich, 1955-1958 (Box-folder 4: 12)
    - Kuzzen, Nikolas, 1933 (Box-folder 4: 13)
    - Lakshmiswar, Sinha, 1931 (Box-folder 4: 14)
    - Lange, Lidiia, 1913-1969 (Box-folder 4: 15-16)
    - Lesishin, Stepan Ivanovich, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 4: 17)
    - Libers, Aleksandro, 1930 (Box-folder 4: 18)
    - Linzil, A., 1929 (Box-folder 4: 19)
    - Lysikov, Valerii, 1938 (Box-folder 4: 20)
    - Malova, M., 1957 (Box-folder 4: 21)
    - Mikelson, E., 1940 (Box-folder 4: 22)
    - Mikhailov, Sergei Alekseevich, 1957 (Box-folder 4: 23)
    - Moelke, Martha, 1949 (Box-folder 4: 24)
    - Morlon, A. S., 1910-1911 (Box-folder 4: 25)
    - Nasledov, Boris Nikolaevich, 1911 (Box-folder 4: 26)
    - Nguen-van, Joan, 1962 (Box-folder 4: 27)
    - Niukvest, Irina Vadimovna, 1958 (Box-folder 4: 28)
    - Novik, Sergei Mikhailovich, 1958-1964 (Box-folder 4: 29)
    - Parizch, Johannes, 1930 (Box-folder 4: 30)
    - Petrulis, I., 1959 (Box-folder 4: 31)
    - Pisarev, Vladimir Prokof'evich, 1956 (Box-folder 4: 32)
    - Podkatiner, S., 1958 (Box-folder 4: 33)
    - Potikha, Z. A., 1956 (Box-folder 4: 34)
    - Prapuolenis, A., 1956 (Box-folder 4: 35)
    - Radionov, Evsei, 1935 (Box-folder 4: 36)
    - Randolph, Grace, 1910-1915 (Box-folder 4: 37)
    - Robkins, 1922-1923 (Box-folder 4: 38)
    - Rudnev, E., 1958-1959 (Box-folder 4: 39)
    - Ryder, E. M., 1910-1912 (Box-folder 4: 40)
    - Saar, V., 1956-1965 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - Sakharov (Saharov), A. A., 1931-1949 (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - Sarychev, S. V., 1956 (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - Sennacieca Asocio Tutmonda, 1958 (Box-folder 5: 4)
    - Serebrennikova, E. I., 1956-1957 (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - Serysheva, V., 1960 (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - Shabalin, Aleksandr Dmitrievich, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 5: 7)
    - Shabanov, Ivan Vasil'evich, 1935-1956 (Box-folder 5: 8)
    - Shteinberg (Steinberg), Liudmila, 1930 (Box-folder 5: 9)
    - Simeonov, Borislav, 1955 (Box-folder 5: 10)
    - Sittmann, Erna, 1931 (Box-folder 5: 11)
    - Sparkman, Robert, 1911 (Box-folder 5: 12)
    - Stamatiadis, Anakreon, circa 1929 (Box-folder 5: 13)
    - Stamer, R., 1932 (Box-folder 5: 14)
    - Stelmachers, S., 1933 (Box-folder 5: 15)
    - Surzhanenko, Petr Emel'ianovich, 1936 (Box-folder 5: 16)
    - Thormodsen, Olav, 1920-1930 (Box-folder 5: 17)
    - Toll, B. K., 1956-1960 (Box-folder 5: 18-19)
    - Tonti, Antonina Romanovna, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 5: 20)
    - Treimanis, A., 1958-1960 (Box-folder 5: 21)
    - Usova, Valentina, 1930-1931 (Box-folder 5: 22)
    - Veselov, G., 1957 (Box-folder 5: 23)
    - Vishnevskii, Vladimir, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 5: 24)
    - Vodavonovich, James, 1907-1920 (Box-folder 5: 25)
    - Volokhov, Anatolii, 1935-1956 (Box-folder 5: 26)
    - Voronkovskaia, E., 1958-1960 (Box-folder 5: 27)
    - Wahnschafft, M., 1923 (Box-folder 5: 28)
    - Watzinger, Franz, 1922-1923 (Box-folder 5: 29)
    - Weckmann-Wittenburg, J. F., 1923 (Box-folder 5: 30)
    - Zafer, 1930 (Box-folder 5: 31)
    - Zausmer, Stanislaw, 1958 (Box-folder 5: 32)
- Photographs, 1911-1957
  - Bagi, Uilio, 1932 (Box-folder 5: 33)
  - Gasparian, Alfred Akopovich, 1957 (Box-folder 5: 33)
  - Jevsejeva (Evseeva), Liudmila Ivanovna, 1937 (Box-folder 5: 34)
  - Kranke, Marianne, 1930 (Box-folder 5: 34)
  - Lakshmiswar, Sinha, 1931 (Box-folder 5: 34)
  - Latvian and Estonian Esperanto Society, group portraits, 1931-1939 (Box-folder 5: 33)
    Includes photographs depicting G. Tupitsyn with Society members.
  - Morariu, Tiberio, circa 1920 (Box-folder 5: 35)
  - Novik, Sergei Mikhailovich, 1951 (Box-folder 5: 35)
  - Tartu Esperanto language conference participants, Estonia, 1936 (Box-folder 5: 35)
  - Xnox, K., 1911 (Box-folder 5: 35)
- Speeches and Writings, 1918-1964
  - General, 1920-1957 (Box-folder 5: 36-37)
    Includes short articles, notes, and drafts.
  - "Anekdotoj," typescript, 1957 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - "Bela historio," manuscript, 1938 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - "Cu la libro ne estas mirarklo?," typescript, circa 1930 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - "Latyshsko-Esperantskii slovar'," first part, manuscript, circa 1930 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - "Mia reports en la Balta kongreso esperantista en Rigo, Kastels," speeches, typescripts, 1918-1961 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - "Russko-Esperantskii slovar'," manuscript, 1934-1960 (Box-folder 6: 6-8)
    Includes notes, drafts, and requests for the dictionary.
  - "Uchebnik Iazyka esperanto," typescript, 1957-1964 (Box-folder 6: 9-11, Box-folder 7: 1-2)
    Includes notes, drafts, and printed matter.
- Printed Matter, 1908-1991
  - General, 1908-1991 (Box-folder 7: 3-4)
    Includes leaflets, newsletters, calendars, and clippings.
  - "Nia Informilo," Instrua kaj literatura gazeto, Eldono de la Esperanto-Instituto Isosek, 1930-1931 (Box-folder 7: 5-6)
  - Enciklopedia Vortaro Esperanta-German, unia-kvara parto, by Eugen Wuster, Leipzig, 1918 (Box-folder 7: 7-10)